hello I'm your host David Barnard and
with me today Revenue cat CEO Jacob idy
Our Guest today is Adam allore the
founder and CEO of wave boating wave
provides a better Marine navigation
experience that is easy collaborative
and fun on the podcast we talk with Adam
about Landing PR for a niche app
negotiating strategic Partnerships and
how pretending to have an app helped
validate that he should actually build
one hey Adam thanks so much for joining
us on the podcast today thanks so much
for having me uh huge fan of the show so
it's an honor to be here and Jacob nice
to see you on a Friday morning David
it's my dream we got to talk about apps
we talk about boats we get to talk about
strategic Partnerships I'm thrilled
let's go yeah I do want to dig into
strategic Partnerships I think it's
something more apps should seek out and
I think you got a lot of really great
lessons that other apps can learn from
in that respect but before we get there
I think it'll help to have a little bit
of context around What wave boating is
so tell us the story how did you get
started with W boating and what is it
yeah sure thing so I went to school for
mechanical engineering and to pay for
that education I worked at marinas and
while there I kind of realized people
really struggled with reading nautical
charts and it's a fairly crucial point
to be able to have a good day on the
water kind of knowing where you're going
and not ultimately running a ground so
fast forward five six seven years I'm
working as an engineer climbing the
corporate ladder there and I really
didn't have a lot of opportunity to be
creative so I had this side project in
my head which was I'm going to rethink
how a nautical chart looks like the
traditional nautical chart the way it's
designed is so that it's easy to Mark
with a pencil and it reduces ink when
printed so thought I was like okay in
digital age let's re-evaluate how this
thing looks and I want to make it custom
to me as a boater and to my vessel and
the initial concept was where you go on
like a personal watercraft or a jet ski
which only draws six inches into the
water versus a sailboat that draws six
feet into the water those vessels have
very different places where they can go
especially when they're a close to shore
I want to build a map that would just
show me where I could go in blue and
where I couldn't go in red you know in a
sense kind of like dumbing down the
experience so you don't have to know how
to read a topographic submarine map
right exactly like just try and keep it
as simple as possible and so my goal
initially was I want to build a map that
I would use so I was using some free GIS
mapping software I got a sample of
nautical Digital Data from Canadian
hydrographic Services a Canadian company
here and just started messing around and
built a map that I was excited by and
that I would actually use out on the
water so completed this project was
excited was proud of what we had and
then coincidentally 2 weeks later I
learned that there's a boat show in the
area and this is where my life started
to go down more an entrepreneurial
Avenue where I was like you know what
what the heck I'm gonna get a booth at
this show I'm GNA see if anyone else
likes my map essentially so I took this
map I hosted it on a web page and added
it to the home screen on a couple iPads
so it looks like it was an app but it
was just totally a dynamic map on a web
page and went to this show and was like
oh right you got to have a company name
right so name this company well wave
with two v's asking why well the domain
name for wave with one V was taken so
went for the double vs and away we went
and went boo had a booth had a couple
iPads there had this map and it was one
of those weird experiences where things
go better than you expected I was just
getting tons of positive feedback of
people seeing this map of this area
saying hey I really like this like I
want to use this and then I was also
seeing people starting to get a little
attraction at the booth here going into
the app stores and trying to find wave
with
2vs and coming up with nothing and be
like where's your app I can't see this
and I was like oh okay give me your
emails we're in beta your emails I'll
let you know when this thing gets
released and that was the point for me
to realize that I had something and I
was going to pursue something I was
still working full-time as an engineer
at that point and and the quantity
emails that we got was one thing but
seeing people kind of light up and get
excited by that map and that experience
that I built that was what gave me that
confidence to quit my job and pursue
this thing full-time and make this beta
a reality that I was telling people
about how much did it cost the booth do
you remember all in all probably less
than $ thousand dollars that's good
that's not bad you know a fake app that
you built side hustle with your GIS and
a $1,000 booth and I mean more
entrepreneurs should be that Scrappy to
go validate your idea with a fake iPad
app are you just unshame I think a lot
of people would get afraid of that
because they'd be like oh I don't want
to be caught right like I don't want to
seem like I'm something I'm not and like
stuff like this but and then I think
other people are just like I don't care
what other people think and they'll try
things you know no there was tons of
impostor syndrome going on at the time I
me but apparently cuz you literally were
an imposter at that point so I think
probably an okay diagnosis remove the
syndrome part I would right always makes
it easier right then it's not really a
syndrome then it's just it's just truth
I've just seen so many people like I
have this app idea and then they go hire
a contractor or they spend six months
building it themselves so by the time
they get any Market validation they're
either like months and months of their
own time or they're even figures in the
hole Yeah $50,000 upside down before
they even get any level of Market
validation and L
pictures a lot of people listen to this
podcast probably are the app person in
somebody's life right so you've gotten
the pitch hey I got an app idea I just
need somebody to build it and I'm like
well have you literally like drawn it
out and asked people like would you use
this have you like done any interviews
have you built it with a spreadsheet
that's my favorite when people pitch me
something I'm like you know this would
work with just like a spreadsheet and
you could operate it out of email like
you should try that first and see if
people care right or in your case just
like a picture and see if there's any
response whatsoever I mean this is I
don't know I guess part of the show's
thing but that I think it causes a ton
of failure to start for people because
people don't go just like what is the
bare minimum investment and like $1,000
that's even kind of pricey but if you're
thinking about launching on something
like just heads up $1,000 going out of
your pocket is going to be something you
have to get used to like when you're
you're trying to build a business right
exactly and I'm kind of weighing at this
point like a career change right like do
I leave my comfortable engineering
position there to go full risk so for a
thousand bucks it seemed worthwhile at
the time yeah even if it had been a
negative result it also would have been
worthwhile at the time because you
wouldn't have ruined your life trying
build an app what he cares about right
right on so you get this initial
excitement at the boat show you've got
emails of people but you've got no beta
to actually send them which you promise
them what's the next step in the journey
to actually build that beta and start
actually building an app yeah so I knew
I wanted to build something first my
Approach wasn't run out for investment
at this point it was get to the next
level seen that excitement in people
eyes that's great that's one thing would
people open up their wallets and give a
credit card number was sort of the next
thing that I ultimately wanted to
validate so my thinking was okay I've
got the skill sets that I can work on
these Maps I can build the maps mobile
Dev is where I'm lacking and I'm going
to start with an IOS app so I found a
local contractor to essentially build
that wrapper so that we could put these
maps on an iOS device and I could get
some early traction with that so worked
closely with this contractor was just
self-funding this aspect of it paying
for that development to get something
out in the store as quickly as possible
and admittedly like it was bad like it
was it was very bad it had the map
people like the map but everything
around it was like bare bare minimum but
it was I think in hindsight enough to
draw an attention from early adopters
just what I needed at that point and
that's the key I think a lot of folks
missed too is like in the idea of an MVP
the minimal viable product you had the
viable part it was the map people Lov
the map the map was the True Value prop
and so rather than focusing on the fluff
you got that valuable part out and
people cared oh I mean in fact it's the
right way to do it cuz if one there's
the investment aspect right it but
probably cost you 10 times as much to
make it two times better right or
something like that that in terms of
like having like a good experience or
like getting App Store Rewards or
whatever your benchmark is but the worst
part is that that I think actually hide
signal right because if you can get
people excited about a crappy app it's
not going to be scalable right because
it's crappy right because it's got
problems but if you can get people
actually using it despite all and that's
the hidden secret of launching an MVP
it's one half is about it is moving fast
the other half is you really shouldn't
work on something unless it's got such a
pull from the market that you're going
to get people using it despite the
problems because that really tells you
there's a need you know if you build a
really pretty app you might like load
people into the app for those reasons
and it's just not going to be that
sticky because honestly that stuff is
pretty replicable right like making a
decent app experience like you can spend
money and create that having like a
unique product ins sight that's more
rare that's where your margin's going to
come from and you should test that in
that first MVP and if you get anything
then it's signal that's kind of a
continuation of what you did with the
boat show right it's like what's the
minimum I can spend to get some
validation and then like do that again
right and I'm gonna guess the next stage
was to do that again yeah and just keep
going and then I mean from there it was
starting to prove people would actually
pay for this solution and I'll step back
a little bit like as much as recognizing
that the map was so important like the
yearly MVP we did add in other feature
sets and functionalities and just
realized that those weren't ringing true
with people like there was an emergency
response functionality to it that
thought was oh this is gonna be amazing
everyone's gonna love it this is why
this thing's goingon to Skyrocket but it
just kind of came back to like no we
just like the map I was like okay all
right focus on that but then yeah
naturally the next thing was then how do
we get some traction with this you know
the build it and they will come
unfortunately isn't really true at least
in my experience you kind of have to
drum up some excitement and get some
people coming in and downloading it so
that was sort of the next thing it's not
a completely clear Market you're coming
into right there are other antical chart
apps and things like that even with a
different take like you're going to have
to find some wedge and figure out how to
like steal Market Shar and
so yeah what was that wedge for you you
had those emails but I imagine that was
like tens to low hundreds of emails by
the time you got to launch so that's not
enough to really I mean it's enough to
like get some validation but not enough
to like really Kickstart a real business
so what was that first step to start
getting real traction yeah it was really
took an engineering mind testing
approach from there kind of a shotgun to
marketing so tried everything that was
available on paid acquisition at the
time Facebook ads let's try a little bit
there let's try a little Google search
run a test I think I was doing you know
$500 $1,000 maximum spend test Apple
search ads was just actually been out
for maybe a year or two that one was
actually one of the wins out of all the
tests there I remember looking back now
like think we're getting downloads for
like 50 cents or a dollar the good old
days ask my wife for a loan or something
and just it all there I don't yeah
because you you were still like doing
all this out of your own pocket right
yep still self-funding and you know I
had the luxury of I'd worked as an
engineer for seven years prior to that
so I had some savings to give this some
breathing room and then tested other
things too like going around to marinas
with my drone to take aerial footage to
see if they put up a poster this is one
of the failed attempts realized that to
get find people to find a time to then
come and take photo of their Marina to
then print out a poster for them to then
put it up to then get the amount of
activation on it like it just did not
make any sense but it was one of those
things you got to try and fail and then
one of the things I was particularly
successful was actually getting some PR
hits on the app itself what I was kind
of realizing especially that there's
some advantages being in the Marine
space is one wasn't particularly inated
with Mobile Solutions and a lot of the
articles in the Marine space were kind
of the same old story you know Mercury
Marines got a new o board with like 15
more horsepower same story we've heard
for the past 50 years so I thought
there's a cool angle here mobile
solution I haven't really touched on it
but like there's a ways feature set like
Community element to the app itself
people are sharing points of interest
which is unique I think from other
products in the market right exactly
exactly so that was kind of a community
element was exciting and so what I did
with the journalists was recognize like
they have a very difficult job I think
especially today when there's just so
much pressure for them to create content
so my thought was like how can I make
their life easier and so what I did was
first get a huge list of journalists who
were writing in the Marine space and
then basically wrote the article for
them had all the image ready to go so
like this if they wanted it was like
drag and drop ready to go here's your
piece of content that you needed to
execute today done some would still want
to do an interview and actually create
their own content and obviously would
absolutely facilitate that but that was
one of those strategies that was was
helpful to start getting some
credibility and people publishing and
writing about wave that's really cool I
think a lot of people underestimate that
aspect of making it easy on a journalist
to tell your story but the other part
you didn't really dive into it but the
storytelling part like what was the
story you were telling because I think
that's a huge part of getting pressed is
like you said so many in the Marine
space are having to write the next story
of this outboard has 15 more horsepower
like that's just
boring but it's what's going on in the
industry how did you tell a story that
was compelling enough to get those
picked up I think it was just kind of
circling back on the problems that I was
seeing when I was working at a Marina
and recognizing that anyone writing the
Marine space that would sort of resonate
with them so one of the aspects of the
application was the community aspect and
I think that added the exciting part to
it so the story there was sort of this
here's his application that can allow
anyone to boat like a local wherever
they go so in wave boating people are
marking points of interest you know Ming
locations Beach locations fishing
locations super helpful like by the way
there's a trailer at this boat ramp
under the water that somebody left or
something you know what I mean there's
always like weird things you don't know
you go to a lake you never been to
before that only somebody who's been
there a lot probably knows right exactly
and that's kind of unique with the Marin
there's so much knowledge but it's in
people's heads and quickly tanging one
of the hypothesis there was like would
people actually share that if they were
given that opportunity that wasn't a
known when we started the application
was like you know I had this thought
that people would share you don't know
like we weren't paying them we weren't
really incentivizing them but sure
enough people do share they can help if
they can and that's really exciting so
that Community aspect of it I think was
the exciting Story part it also was a
little less technical than diving into
the mapping aspects of it it's easier to
write about than yeah yeah and so really
sort of focusing on that part of the
solution was what was getting picked up
I mean I think that highlights like we
try press stuff here you know it's all
about us pitching like you said making
their job easy right like come up with a
story that's compelling and don't be too
Shish right like don't just be like show
my product you know I got 15 more
horsepower whatever right and there's a
ton of these in these Niche anywhere
there's like a high spend Niche Aviation
has these like boating has these any
sort of sports activity there's trade
that people get they go out you know I
get several for like random
organizations I'm a part of and things
like this and I imagine probably in
terms of like you compare in Tech Broad
tech Publications which really aren't
even that like Niche anymore they're
just Publications compared to like
something that's not Tech but it's
specifically for your customers like
that's a really high Roi Place probably
in terms of how much it costs to
actually address that also people
selling boat motors they've got like
manufacturing margins you've got
software margins right you can afford
you can afford probably when it comes to
like spending into those things and
things like that you have margin
advantage AG to reaching that audience
which is the nice part about building
apps right absolutely so skipping ahead
a bit some influential people started
picking up on that press so tell me
about seu and them reaching out to you
after seeing some press around wave yeah
and I think that ties into one of the
main learnings from that press Outreach
was initially when I kicked it off I
thought it would be a main push from
straight user acquisition and it did add
value I probably at the time thought it
was going to make this big hockey stick
growth once we get this one article
published that wasn't the case but like
it obviously helped bring you know yeah
exactly you know first time found here
with this company right so always
leading with optimism what I did see
come out of that aside from yes some
user acquisition was this is how we were
getting recognized within the space and
getting some Outreach and so this big
break happened here where bombard
Recreational Products they the largest
manufacturer and personal watercraft seu
reached out and wanted to talk about an
integration and so the story that I've
heard from them is that we got a PR hit
in province of Quebec bombard
recreational prods is based in Montreal
and I guess their chief engineer had
used the app that weekend and liked it
like the map again and thought it would
be a good fit for their target market
and they were looking at doing
essentially like a carplay Android auto
like solution for some future models of
cuu so creating an integration where an
app could actually run on their units so
Rider connects their phone and then it
renders versions of the application on
like an LCD screen just ahead of the
handlebars so BRP reaches out and says
hey we would love you to be the nav
Solution on this platform I'm still
running this company out of the basement
of the house that I'm
renting that's when you CC your
assistant that doesn't exist
right let me let me reach out to my
assistant and schedule a
call I'm both excited and terrified for
anyone from BRB to listen to this
podcast
but it's all in already right yeah
exactly this is just a fun story so
extremely excited by that Outreach and
so at the time yeah the pitch was hey
like we want you to use our software
development kit to make this integration
possible technically what we had to do
was the inter face is controlled by like
like your TV remote like a four-way
controller with a okay button in the
middle so you had to like rethink how
the app works with that sort of human
machine interface which had its own set
of challenges related to it so we had to
integrate onto that and of course they
wanted it for IOS and Android didn't
have an Android app at this point in
time is it actually using carplay or is
it it's it's no it's their own solution
so tell me about negotiating this step
me through the process because I think
there's an opportunity for a lot of apps
to make their own own way with
Partnerships not just get press and wait
for somebody to reach out to you but
actually reach out to folks and try and
do things like this but okay you reach
out to this huge Behemoth in the field
or they reach out to you but now you got
to step through like how do we arrange
this financially like do I bring lawyers
on like tell me that stepbystep process
of how you went from them having some
level of interest to then actually
inking a deal the biggest thing that was
over arching in the whole negotiation
process that I learned was like for BRP
looking at us like we are a risk I think
for any big company to say hey I want to
partner with you and I would imagine for
a lot of people in the app space r was
listening like you're going to be
probably considered as a risk for these
organizations so my goal throughout the
entire process was just to mitigate that
risk as much as possible someone had
stuck their neck out and was being a
cheerleader to you have a champion it's
just like an like somebody internally
has to be your Champion or it just not
never going to happen yeah and so I
wanted to support that person and I
wanted to drisk us as much as possible
and so it really was just some basic
like one-on-one stuff like being
extremely responsive overd delivering
whatever was asked of us making sure
everything was timely just as we're
going through that process so that
they're kind of feeling a little more
relaxed feel like you're on it right
subtle language the body language of
reliability right yeah so I think that
was one of the biggest things for sure
with that I think also so I recognized
the importance of that partnership for
us as a company at that point in time
like again as a highlight like we early
early days I was in the basement of the
house that we renting knowing that
Landing this partnership would just add
a ton of credibility for the business
user acquisition aside like it was going
to help put the company on the map and
that has a lot of value that like you
put a dollar value to that there's a lot
of like if this doesn't happen we die
scenarios in like early startups right
so it's like how do you put a dollar
value on that right like an Roi versus
this versus not right yeah so I mean I
just kind of took approach not trying to
be particularly greedy with anything
making sure we could commit to something
that I feel could be executed on that
being said you know after sign the
contract of like here's what we're going
to build and when to do it you know
there's some minor panic attacks of like
okay now this needs to be done yeah but
yeah I think drisking not being greedy
recognizing the value building
relationship when things came from more
of a legal standpoint I was bringing in
a guy I went to school with who you say
you got have cheap legal somewhere you
get absolutely that's when you're
tapping your friends on the shoulder and
he was really instrumental in terms of
walking me through like what does this
legal LE mean what do I have to be
concerned about and so thankfully that
partnership was fairly smooth I think
bombard recordal products came from a
very collaborative mindset and they were
excited to work with us and we were able
to sort of facilitate that and
ultimately deliver on that partnership
for what you can share what was the
structure
of the arrangement the way it works
there is a rider on the COO itself still
has to get a subscription to our service
to be able to use it on their cuu so
they're not paying you per usage no so
the consumers there now we've since then
have generated like a discounted type
offering for anyone who buys AUM my
pitch was like they're buying a $20,000
cuu let's give them a $45 app let's
facilitate that that was the main thing
there and then they helped a bit with
some of the integration costs up front
so that helped actually bring in a
little bit of essentially first
investment into the company oh yeah I
mean I think sometimes people don't
think about these deals as creatively as
they can be built like I've Heard lots
of different ones and it depends on the
stage you're at and things like this
right but yeah sometimes it can be a
Strategic investment for Equity or
sometimes it can just be like hey we'll
help offset the cost of development
along with this I think your point about
not being greedy is really important
just being self-aware about who stands
to gain from what here you don't want to
be taken advantage of obviously you
don't want to be run over but like being
very flexible especially if it's
something you're experimenting with I
think there's deals that I mean as a
Founder I think you can just kind of
smell like uh I don't think this is
goingon to be worth the squeeze and you
should be careful just because some
company you look up to is trying to talk
to you about that we've had that here
where I think the biggest one for us is
people always want to like partner and
buy like data sets and stuff from us and
these really big companies and like we
have like a moral obligation not to do
that but you're like who got in touch
with us they want to part you almost
want to be like how much and you're like
no like no can't do that right but I
think it is possible as like a small
company to get Star Struck talking to
big companies and then you can end up so
there's a balance there but yeah you got
to be flexible and assume it's not your
last contract you know potentially with
them and potentially with the next
partner and stuff like that right
reminds me very much of how we were
doing our very first contracts with
customers here it's like well legal I
just read contracts right like it's in
English right like use a good template
like they want to change something I'm
like it's probably harmless is this
going to be what kills us you know
there's a limit to that obviously but
again if your company's worth nothing
what's the risk to signing a contract
you probably don't have any personal
liability right if you're coming at it
in good faith and using your head things
tend to work out but yeah you really do
just gotta make it happen right you got
to figure it out and where' you go from
there so you signed the contract with
cidu and they pay you something but
you're still in your basement did you
raise money at that point and build a
team around you to deliver this was
there anybody working with you when you
were going through this deal or was it
just you there was one the iOS
contractor yeah when you go to meet the
team I have this moment we were pitching
a company that was like 300 people at
Revenue cat like very early days it was
like 2018 Miguel and I went and it was
me and Miguel and like 10 other people
in the room and it was like o and then
they asked how many people on our team
and I lied and said five even though it
was like two what is the reasonable
sounding number yeah EX I was like but
you think five makes him feel any
better when you're two I guess it does
yeah yeah there's others that's what I
should have said there's others oh yeah
yeah Jim is sick today Sarah couldn't
make it yeah sorry I had to share that
story no totally relatable and that was
the position I was in ultimately like I
said there was totally like a oh my
goodness Panic moment but excitement at
the same time so the advantage I had now
at this point was the IOS app
application was in the store I had
proven that people would actually pay
for it and then I had a contract with
BRP to do something really cool so with
that I was able to go out to the local
Angel Network here to raise some capital
and wasn't anything crazy less than half
a million dollars but that was enough to
get things going build up a bit more of
a team get the Android application
deliver on BRP and grow and go from
there and then since partnering with
brpc do you've had other partnership so
let's talk through that next partnership
with Freedom Boat Club and this was
another they reached out to you so tell
me the story of that yeah this is
another fun one so Freedom Boat Club is
like an alternative to owning a vessel
so you pay a monthly due to into a club
and you can take their boats from groups
of locations what had happened was one
of their team members at their largest
Club in Tampa Bay had read about us in
one of the largest Marine industry
magazines and was like this is really
cool I'm going to reach out and so I was
like okay great opportunity I wanted to
get in touch with freedom B Club side
note the guy who reached out to us is
now actually on our team as our director
of marketing so this can also work as a
talent acquisition tool everything's a
talent acquisition tool this podcast is
a talent acquisition tool depends on the
time you know yeah yeah so multiple
benefits going on so with them again
what I wanted to do was come from the
mindset of like well how can we help and
I think that's another main point is
like come from a position of like how
can you help first and then go from
there and does your solution support
support that and then in some cases
there may be a thing where it's like I
really don't think we can help you as
well as another solution possibly could
and then you carry on from there but
with freedom they wanted to prevent
their members from running a ground and
having the best time on the water and
the vessels are their assets so they're
incentivized to keep them in the water
so okay excellent let's provide licenses
to this solution to all of your members
and cut down on incident rates and
maximize their time on the water so they
continue to be a free and bow Club
member and so that was essentially the
deal that we set up with them and was my
first fora into I guess more direct B2B
sales where we were then selling
licenses to wave directly to the club so
that their members could use it so from
the members perspective it was like they
were getting a free app from the club's
perspective it was a much cheaper
solution than like outfitting the
vessels with multi thousand chart
plotters which are like the right preapp
solution saving money for them it's not
just some like tack on I think that's I
mean we Heard lots of customers there's
a lot of companies doing these B2B side
motions and it has some challenges
contractually like building the deals
it's a very different motion than
building an app in terms of go to market
motion it's just a very different beast
but ultimately yeah you're right it's
like selling a per license thing how
much pain was there in making the flows
and stuff work did you guys have to
invest a lot there was it the first time
you've done that in terms of like making
sure that your members have access and
things like that yeah it was an extra
challenge so I think architecturally I
think we ended up going with like a deep
linking solution so that we could
actually get them past our traditional
payall as possible exactly and that was
one of the things I learned there was
like at least with these early
Partnerships like you can kind of go
nuts thinking about how people could
gamify it and everything else like that
oh people hate being stolen from it
makes people crazy you know what I mean
like you're going to create all this
like crazy rub Goldberg machine of
authentication and whatever when it's
like just figure out a way to make sure
that all the people that are actually
paying have the best experience possible
and accept the little spillage Maybe
right exactly and then my thought was
well if that's a problem we'll make sure
we've got mechanisms for self- policing
after the fact and we can go in and
clean things up but let's make sure we
make it as easy for people to get
activated and that was probably one of
the biggest learnings there was in this
process we were talking about this sort
of activation type and everything else
like that the biggest thing was it's
most important just to make it super
easy for that person to actually use
this application that was the biggest
hurdle there is like there's a behavior
change that we have to create for these
members which is here's this new app
they've never heard about that's now
offering to them as a club how do you
actually get them to click on that email
and do that activation
remind know they even have access to it
right that's the biggest challenge than
any of the technical aspects of it and
were you getting paid per Activation so
you were incentivized to activate them
versus getting paid like a flat fee per
250 members in the club and you would
get a fee on all 250 or only the ones
that would activate we've done
experimentation with both for that
particular one it was based on a per
activation rate I mean it's smart like
you guys are going to know more how to
get people to open an app and things
like that but yeah I think that's you
know you talk about renewals are these
Partners going to renew on this I think
they're going to want to see data
they're going to want to know like our
customers actually and so this is
classic B Tob sit right you don't want
to sell a deal you put a lot of work
into a deal if it CHS after it's first
period like that's a waste you probably
just spend that first period of the deal
making back all your investment cost to
like get the deal going right if you're
lucky you only have a onee payback
period it's really important to think
about that in the structure of the deal
think about how in this deal can we
structure it that like we're
incentivized to make it successful and
they're incentivized as well to make it
successful because you know
organizations are big you lose track of
stuff I think that's been my biggest
learning with Partnerships we've tried a
few on and off and unless like there are
champions on both sides like highly
motivated and you know for you guys it's
a growth channel it's never been a huge
growth channel for us at least when I
was in the early days when somebody
approached me I'd just be like ah I'd
have to put a lot of energy into this
and I think it does not rise above like
the other opportunities I have so it's
almost as important to know when not to
do them because they can like pull you
in if you're not ready to commit I can
totally relate to and we got burned by
that too there's a couple successes
there but there's definitely been some
lessons learned don't if call them
failures but one of the examples was
this was foring with a partnership with
a bow rental company and they wanted
some webbased solution to manage their
members that were using the application
as well and at the time I was like okay
let's you know I've had a couple wins
here I'm going to continue down this
Avenue again and then at the end of the
day what sort of happening was I just
felt like we end up becoming almost like
really cheap Dev op company solution for
them we're building a custom solution
for them and I'm proud of what we build
they happy that's great but then you
know I built something for addressable
Market of one and maybe I actually could
have gone and taken that solution and
maybe sold it to other B rental
companies but then I don't know that
business that's a different business and
as I think you're High Jacob like
there's a million and three things to do
every day you got to be careful it can
absolutely be a distraction and that
happened to us where it was like hm I
wonder how much straight consumer at
product development we might have lost
during that perod of time counterfactual
like whatever you didn't do because you
were doing that instead yeah and like
you know we're small team growing
there's tradeoffs so hard to say no to
anybody to that point right you're like
just trying to scrap I always say like
anybody who cares about my stupid app
meaning Revenue cat in this case like
anybody who cares about Revenue cat like
I want to talk to and I want to make
happy right Partnerships can be a
classic trap there where you end up it
same with investors too like it's really
easy I think to be flattered sometimes
as a Founder just because you're used to
everybody ignoring you so it's like it's
like it could be a bit of a email right
but like you said too it's the you know
and I think with especially in like
niches I think if you're building a mass
consumer product unless you're going to
do a partnership with Pepsi or something
insane then that's going to be very hard
to like pull off at a small scale we've
seen it work with some other I mean we
talked to I don't know if Alex mcgreg
talked about this on the podcast or not
they make an app for plant owners plant
parents you know they've done some
Partnerships with plant Sellers and
things like this that had some success
which outside of niches you never would
have talked about this 10 years ago
right it's just kind of the state of
maturation penetration like willingness
for Consumer to try these things and
it's a strategy I think a lot of people
should be considering yeah Alex did
share that on the podcast and then I've
followed up with him since and they've
continued to expand those and are
rolling out even bigger Partnerships and
it's been a huge success and a huge
driver for them of user acquisition
getting these little QR codes put in
every plant that's sold at these
nurseries and now they've rolled that
into bigger and bigger plant sellers so
I'm curious for you how these
Partnerships have worked out from an
actual user acquisition standpoint has
it really driven user acquisition and
helped Drive revenue or has it been more
about that recognition and press and
other things that have driven it from a
end around I think honestly a bit of
both so straight user acquisition
probably we're looking at 25% of our
total user acquisition is coming through
like our partnering
facilitation now we also know that a lot
of people who are coming from our
organic channels I.E like untracked I
guess is what we probably call it I've
also heard about us from these other
things as well the virality and the
influence of those users right and then
probably some who just aren't tracked
properly right exactly yeah there's that
knock on value that's kind of hard to
sttion especially I think with Marine
space and with boating like there's a
natural viral element to yeah I mean
that's the niche element Advantage too
right if you have a smaller more dense
niche of hobbyists like there's a better
K factor or whatever in in virality I
think than in the general population
yeah so there's been a direct and
positive benefit and it's clearly part
of our continued user acquisition
strategy and then the other hard to
measure benefit is absolutely The
credibility piece when we're looking at
other potential Partnerships people
aren't familiar with us they know about
bombard recreational prodcts they know
about Freedom Boat Club they know about
some of our other partners that we work
in the boat education and Licensing
spaces so there's certainly credibility
there that can open those doors and
maybe it's not a partnership but it's
maybe just some other sort of thing
that's getting facilitated yeah it's
very interesting I think how you took it
from the Press stuff and use that to
trade up into Partnerships and then
trade those up into bigger Partnerships
and it's a whole game of aside from just
different growth mechanisms but like in
building something you're always taking
what you have and leveraging it into the
next thing it's like that gift with the
little Domino into the bigger bigger
bigger Domino right that's leverage
right that's a perfect illustration of
how to like take advantage of Leverage
and so it's good to have a balanced
approach and be like we don't just look
at the dollars and sense of a
partnership right like it's the dollars
and sense of it but then there's also
like the Priceless aspect of it of like
what does this create for us and I feel
like as a Founder you kind of know like
you kind of know when you did a Founders
ship or something and it was like yeah
it doesn't really seem like this move
the needle for US versus one where
you're like bringing it up it's coming
up people BR mention it to you may not
be perfectly measurable but you're like
I feel like this did something right and
I think that's okay we don't have to
have perfect attribution to these things
right have you leveraged those
Partnerships in Social proof so I was
actually surprised not to see any
mention of the CDU partnership like in
your app store screenshots or anything
like that do you feel like those kind of
Partnerships help with consumers to see
that your real app with these big
Partnerships and stuff I think first off
one there's probably a bit of a missed
opportunity for us to actually have that
on our product pages um you got to go
back and get logo rights in that deal
you know I made that mistake to the
early days yeah yeah that's where legal
gets back involved so I think there's
definitely value there where I kind of
saw this interesting flywheel happen is
then you land the partnership and then
there becomes another press release
right oh yeah yeah and then you just
kind of get back into their press team
is like motivated to share it too right
it's like something they can put on
their social ideally is bigger than your
social right yeah and so then there's
this other harder untangle benefit of
that partnership spinning your PR again
to then hopefully facilitate another
opportunity we do need to wrap up any
other top lessons anything you would
advise other app Founders in thinking
about how to leverage strategic
Partnerships in their business yeah I
think just consider how you can help
start with that what's the advantage of
them working with you and how can you
make a difference in their business at
the end of the day and even thinking of
it from like a p&l standpoint like it
needs to be something that they see real
value or it's part of maybe their brand
Mission at the time try to drisk the
situation as much as possible overd
deliver be timely don't be greedy and
then just make sure you can deliver on
it and have fun and go from there and as
we're wrapping up anything else you
wanted to share with our esteemed
audience here always looking to work
with awesome people I know we didn't
talk too much about team stuff but all
of this is so much easier if you're
working with good people and it takes a
while so boats and apps don't
temp it's right in my current wheelhouse
so perfect so yeah don't be shy reach
out I love chat with various people in
the space start there and then certainly
you know interested in any sort of
Partnerships with other applications in
the outdoor space that'd be a fun one so
that's you please reach out yeah that's
another kind of underleveraged
opportunity as well like partnering with
other apps in the space or other bigger
apps who have ad inventory that they're
not making good use of Affiliates we
talked with cardpointers about finding
influencers in the space like there's
just a lot of opportunities to partner
with folks and get attention through
that so yeah reach out to Adam and
thanks so much for joining us on the
podcast Adam this was a lot of fun
thanks so much for having
me thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. sub club.com to join
our private
[Music]
community